<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Export generator="Cache" version="25">
<CSP name="copyright.html" application="/csp/docbook/" default="1"><![CDATA[
<HTML>

<HEAD>
<LINK rel=stylesheet href="DocBookHTML.css" type=text/css>
<TITLE>Copyright</TITLE></HEAD>

<BODY>

<TABLE CLASS="Banner" BGCOLOR="#287780" CELLPADDING="0" CELLSPACING="0" WIDTH="100%" BORDER="0">
<TR VALIGN="TOP">
<TD><DIV CLASS="ChapterTitle" ALIGN="LEFT">Cach&eacute; Documentation Copyright Information</DIV></TD>
</TR></TABLE>
<BR>
<HR>
<BR>

<DIV CLASS="para">Copyright &#169; InterSystems Corporation.</DIV>
<DIV CLASS="para">All Rights Reserved.</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">NOTICE: PROPRIETARY &#151; CONFIDENTIAL</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
This document contains trade secret and confidential information which is the property of
InterSystems Corporation, One Memorial Drive, Cambridge, MA 02142, or its affiliates, and is
 furnished for the sole purpose of the operation and maintenance of the products of InterSystems
Corporation. No part of this publication is to be used for any other purpose, and this publication
is not to be reproduced, copied, disclosed, transmitted, stored in a retrieval system or translated
into any human or computer language, in any form, by any means, in whole or in part, without the express
prior written consent of InterSystems Corporation.
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
The copying, use and disposition of this document and the software programs described herein
is prohibited except to the limited extent set forth in the standard software license agreement(s)
of InterSystems Corporation covering such programs and related documentation. InterSystems Corporation
 makes no representations and warranties concerning such software programs other than those set forth
in such standard software license agreement(s). In addition, the liability of InterSystems Corporation
 for any losses or damages relating to or arising out of the use of such software programs is limited
in the manner set forth in such standard software license agreement(s).
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
THE FOREGOING IS A GENERAL SUMMARY OF THE RESTRICTIONS AND LIMITATIONS IMPOSED BY INTERSYSTEMS
CORPORATION ON THE USE OF, AND LIABILITY ARISING FROM, ITS COMPUTER SOFTWARE. FOR COMPLETE INFORMATION
REFERENCE SHOULD BE MADE TO THE STANDARD SOFTWARE LICENSE AGREEMENT(S) OF INTERSYSTEMS CORPORATION,
COPIES OF WHICH WILL BE MADE AVAILABLE UPON REQUEST.
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
InterSystems Corporation disclaims responsibility for errors which may appear in this
document, and it reserves the right, in its sole discretion and without notice, to make
substitutions and modifications in the products and practices described in this document.
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
Cach&eacute; and Ensemble are registered trademarks of InterSystems Corporation.
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
InterSystems, InterSystems Cach&eacute;,  Cach&eacute;  SQL, Cach&eacute; ObjectScript, and
Cach&eacute; Objects are trademarks of InterSystems Corporation.
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
All other brand or product names used herein are trademarks or registered trademarks of their
respective companies or organizations.
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">
For Support questions about any InterSystems products, contact the InterSystems Worldwide Support Center:
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para"><strong>Phone:<br></strong>
US: +1 617 621-0700<br>
Europe: +44 (0) 1753 830-077<br>
<strong>Fax:</strong>   <br>
US: +1 617 374-9391<br>
Europe: +44 (0) 1753 861-311
</DIV>

<DIV CLASS="para">

</DIV>

</body>
</html>


]]></CSP>
</Export>
